CHAPTER 7

Irony as subversion: Thomas Wools ton and the crime of wit

Roger D. Lund

As the first work of British philosophy to fully exploit the subversive potential of irony and ridicule, Hobbes’s Leviathan was also the first to be reviled for a brilliance of style and subtlety of wit that made it seem virtually “unanswerable.”^1 Deists and freethinkers were quick to find in Leviathan a rhetorical model for their own assaults on priestcraft and political tyranny, abandoning more conventional modes of argumentation for the strategic indirection of irony and wit. The adaptation of irony to the demands of religious and philosophical controversy inspired the systematic defense of ridicule as a test of truth given its most memorable form in Shaftesbury’s Essay on the Freedom of Wit and Humor (1708) and Anthony Collins’s Discourse of Irony and Wit in Writing (1729). The efflorescence of heterodox wit also elicited angry rejoinders from critics as various as Lord Clarendon, Richard Blackmore, and Mary Astell, all of whom recognized the power of wit to undermine orthodox assumptions.^2

Treatments of eighteenth-century wit have been limited almost exclusively to discussions of its aesthetic significance, but as we shall see, much of the critical and philosophical debate over the “decorum” of Augustan ridicule disguised a much more fundamental struggle over the very means by which power was to be defended or assailed. This chapter briefly traces the process by which wit first came to be associated with heterodox assaults on established institutions of religion and government, and recounts subsequent attempts to proscribe all forms of rhetorical indirection, including ridicule, innuendo, and wit, as essentially subversive modes of discourse. I focus on the case of Thomas Woolston, whose conviction for blasphemous libel in 1729 crystalized the conflict between orthodox power and heterodox wit, a case in which not the matter of the argument but the witty manner of its presentation provided the grounds for legal prosecution.

I

Responding to the challenge of Leviathan, Isaac Barrow was one of the first who attempted to define the appropriate limits on jesting, a resolution that seemed

especially needful in . .. (this pleasant and jocular age,) which is so infinitely addicted to this sort of speaking, that it scarce doth affect or prize any thing near so much; all reputation appearing now to vail and stoop to that of being a wit... Many at least, to purchase this glory, to be deemed admirable in this faculty, and enrolled among the wits, do not only make shipwreck of conscience, abandon virtue, and forfeit all pretences to wisdom; but neglect their estates, and prostitute their honour.^3

Over the next half century Barrow’s complaints regarding the dangers of unrestrained wit would be elaborated and embellished by a variety of writers, all of whom shared the settled conviction that as modes of argumentation or philosophical discussion, wit and ridicule were fundamentally unfair, inherently impious, and uniquely dangerous. To quote Joseph Glanvill, “Philosophy can shame, and disable all the reasons that can be urged against it. . . jests and loud laughter are not to be confuted; and yet these are of more force to degrade a thing in the esteem of some sort of spirits, than the most potent demonstration.”^4 Glanvill’s response to Hobbes finds an echo in William Warburton’s riposte to Shaftesbury: “RIDICULE having from the hands of a skillful disputant, the same effect in barbarous minds, with the new invented darts of Marius, which, though so weak as to break in the throw, and pierce no farther than the surface, yet sticking there, they more intangle and incommode the combatant, than those arms, which fly stronger, and strike deeper.”^5

Although otherwise an ill-matched pair, Glanvill and Warburton share one fundamental certainty: that ridicule is inherently more dangerous than reasoned argument. The implications of such logic were as far-reaching asthey were seductive: since the liberty of wit led inevitably to witty libertinism, wit, irony, and ridicule were rhetorical forms that called for suppression, by violence if necessary. For Jeremy Collier, that stalwart champion of theatrical probity, witty writing was simply too dangerous to be tolerated, in part because wit hadbecome the hallmark of the atheistical libertine. “One would think Atheism and Lewdness were some very useful Discoveries,” he writes, since “they are so carefully cultivated and improved. With what Magnificence of Art are these Things set off? With what affecting Ideas, points ofWit, and pompous Descriptions? As if it was a glorious Exploit to sap the Foundations of Justice, to strike at the Vitals of Religion, and Debase Mankind into Brutes.” Collier’s diagnosis is common enough; his prescription is not. For he recommends that nothing short of the outright cultivation of dullness can indemnify the age against the dangers of atheistical wit:

What then; must fine Thoughts be stifled, and all the range of Fancy check’d? Is not this to cramp our Understandings, and impose Dullness on the World? Yes, such Restraints without question are great Grievances: If a Man did not Murther now and then, he might possibly forget the Uses of his Weapon. Well, if Sense be so ill Natur’d a Quality, I wish we had less on’t. What if some People have Wit? Must we therefore have no Religion, must the Scriptures be ill Treated, the noblest Professions ridiculed, and the Dignity of Things made an Argument for Contempt? ... To be Museridden at this rate is somewhat hard. If these Outrages are repeated, we must think of reprisals.^6

Modern scholars have often dismissed Collier as a pious crackpot, but his apprehensions as to the dangers of wit were widely shared, as were his calls for official reprisal. Decrying the flood of “Socinian books and pamphlets” that appeared upon the lapse of the Licensing Act in 1695, the Convocation of the Church of England complained bitterly that

Books [previously] written, in an argumentative way, against the Divinity of our blessed Lord, did, in a little time, produce others of a worse spirit and Tendency; wherein the Doctrines, by him reveal’d, were Spoken of with Profane Levity and Contempt, his Humiliation and Sufferings were derided, his Person was blasphem’d, and treated with as Great Indignity and Scorn, as when he stood at the Judgment Seat of Pilate.^7

Like Collier or Glanvill, the Convocation asserts the necessary relationship between heterodox ideas and the “profane levity” that had come to mark heterodox style. They indicate as well their growing conviction that where philosophical or theological arguments were concerned, the rules of engagement had somehow been altered by the introduction of wit.

Writers like Blount and Shaftesbury celebrated the change, defending the role of ridicule and wit in serious discourse and denying that wit was a legitimate cause for official concern.^8 But they were oddities in an age when Collier and the Convocation seemingly defined popular frustration with the misuses of wit. As one might expect, the most strident demands for legal action against licentious and heterodox writers came from those High Churchmen who controlled the Lower House of Convocation. But even Dissenters like Defoe argued that something needed to be done, so great was the threat of libertine wit. “’Twould be endless to examine the Liberty taken by the Men of Wit in the World,” he writes, “the loose they give themselves in Print, at Religion, at Government, at Scandal; the prodigious looseness of the Pen, in broaching new Opinions in Religion, as well as in Politicks, are real Scandals to the Nation, and well deserve a Regulation.”^9

Regulation perhaps, but of what sort? Merely restoring the Licensing Act (a proposal forwarded by some) was clearly no answer, since it served only to censor those who were out of power.^10 And yet, there was a widespread feeling something needed to be done to suppress rhetoric that defied open and direct refutation. As a result defenders of the faith resorted to increasingly strident, if frequently ill-focused, demands that the civil authorities prosecute witty and heretical writers whom they were seemingly unable to confute directly. While few clergymen were as bloodthirsty as Charles Leslie, who suggested that execution was the only appropriate punishment for witty blasphemy, there was general agreement that the government needed to intervene in some fashion to punish those modern infidels who now sat in the seat of the scorner.^11

In the course of the seventeenth century charges of outright blasphemy (with its embarrassing reminders of the auto-da-fé) had gradually given way to trials for seditious or blasphemous libel. Successful prosecution of “contumelious reproaches” against God or the established church seemed far more likely once blasphemous wit had been redefined as a form of sedition that somehow threatened to undermine the foundations of the constitution itself.^12 Such linkage of religious ridicule with presumptive political subversion was one product of a growing concern that the government’s “good name should be maintained, and that the limits of legitimate criticism should be drawn within a narrow compass.”^13 Still smarting from his own misadventures with irony in the Shortest Way With Dissenters, Defoe would write: “Governments will not be jested with, nor reflected upon, nor is it fit that they should always lye at the mercy of every pen.”^14 During the trial of John Tutchin in 1704 Chief Justice Holt argued: “if people should not be called to account for possessing the people with an ill opinion of government, no government can exist.”^15 In other words ridiculing the government or its officers made it contemptible in the eyes of the people and as such weakened its authority. It was an easy step to extend such logic to the ridicule of divine government as well. In Barrow’s terms ridicule

proportionably groweth more criminal, as it presumeth to reach persons eminent in dignity or worth, unto whom special veneration is appropriate. ... It is not only injustice, but profaneness to abuse the gods ... their defects are not to be seen, or not to be touched by malicious or wanton wits, by spiteful or scornful tongues; the diminution of their credit is a public mischief, and the state itself doth suffer in their becoming objects of scorn.^16

Barrow gives voice to an increasingly popular argument that the ridicule of religion was a threat to government as well. Since bishops and clergymen were in effect officers of the crown, ridicule of the clergy was also a libellous assault on the very foundations of the constitution. Legal precedent had been clearly established in Rex v. Taylor [1675] (27 Car. 2.), a case in which Justice Hale had argued “that Christianity is Parcel of the Laws of England; and therefore to reproach the Christian Religion, is to speak in Subversion of the Law.”17 The Taylor case significantly expanded the prerogatives of the criminal courts. It was a decision by which “the court of the King’s Bench invented a new crime,” establishing the precedent that “the common law had jurisdiction over the expression of unorthodox religious opinion,”^18 a precedent that was to have profound implications for the trial of Thomas Woolston. Indeed the equation of the established version of Christianity with the English constitution itself would serve clerical defenders of various kinds of official persecution. Warburton argues that the abuse of the clergy of the sort found in Tindal’s Rights of the Christian Church and Christianity as Old as the Creation is “not only an affront to Religion... but likewise, an insult to civil liberty. For while there is such a thing as a Church established by law, its Ministers must need bear a sacred, that is, a public character ... to abuse them, therefore, as a body is insulting the State which protects them.”^19

Of course had it been the case that those guilty of religious ridicule were actually undermining the stability of the government, penalties for treason might have been more appropriate. Such an argument had been advanced by Sir George Mackenzie, Supreme Justice of the Scottish criminal courts, who in 1678 had defined blasphemy as “divine lease majesty, or Treason,” a decision that eased the process by which Thomas Aikenhead was tried and executed for blasphemy in 1698. Characteristically the legal arguments asserting Aikenhead’s guilt stressed his “scoffing, ridiculing, railing against and cursing the Bible.”^20 However, nettled as they were by the outburst of Socinian pamphleteering that marked the 1690s, even the most vindictive of prelates south of the Tweed were hesitant to demand the ultimate penalty for scoffing at religion, choosing instead to prosecute heterodox texts as forms of seditious or blasphemous libel, a charge sufficiently amorphous to include works of wit. Originally the province of the Star Chamber, responsibility for ferreting out seditious and blasphemous libels after the Restoration devolved variously on the Stationers’ Company, the Houses of Parliament and the courts of common law, most notably the court of the King’s Bench.^21 The common law courts assumed the jurisdiction of the Star Chamber as a “censor morum,” punishing indecency, ribaldry, and blasphemy. The common law courts also assumed the jurisdiction of the ecclesiastical courts and punished the publication of heterodox ideas as tending to sedition and as undermining the “foundations of the Christian faith.”^22

The publication of Matthew Tindal’s Rights of the Christian Church Asserted (1706) reignited the controversy over attempts to suppress wit through civil prosecution. Tindal was vilified as one of those “Libertines” who had attacked the clergy with “the most scurrilous Contempt and scornful Disdain that Profane Wit and Malice could invent.” And he was instantly linked with writers like Blount and Toland, whose works were “fullest of Scandalous Reflections and Profane, Scornful, Impious, Blasphemous Revilings of the Blessed Son of God Christ Jesus and his Religion.”^23 Like his fellow deists Tindal was condemned as a wit whose works cried out for civil prosecution specifically because of their “contumelious” character. Although his book was presented to the Middlesex grand jury and attempts were made to prosecute those who sold the Second Defence of the Rights, Tindal remained largely unmolested by the secular arm.^24 While the Convocation of the Church of England sought to censure Toland’s Christianity Not Mysterious (1696), they found themselves constitutionally incapable ofcensuring any book without license from the king, a license that was never forthcoming.^25 Traditionally, public burning had been the punishment reserved for outrageously heterodox texts like Blount’s Two First Books of Philostratus (1680) and Arthur Bury’s The Naked Gospel (1690), and it was a fate meted out to a variety of works in the eighteenth century.^26 As a means of limiting the spread of heterodox wit, however, public burning proved less than perfect. In 1720 a committee of the House of Lords found Joseph Hall’s anti trinitarian tract A Sober Reply to Mr. Higgs’ Merry Arguments, “a mixture of the most scandalous Blasphemy, Profaneness, and Obscenity; [which] does, in a most daring, impious Manner, ridicule the Doctrine of the Trinity, and all Revealed Religion,” and consigned it to the flames. Ironically, burning books often served as a form of advertisement, and two days after Hall’s book was burned by the common hangman a complaint was made that “a great Number of Books, the same with that ordered to be burnt Yesterday, were dispersed and publickly sold in Westminster Hall, and other Places.”^27

II

While the record for successful prosecution of heterodox works was uneven at best, the threat of civil punishment was nonetheless sufficient to convince many writers that their survival depended on the perfection of a new form of indirect and ironic discourse custom-made to undermine established pieties in religion and government while frustrating the prosecutorial zeal of those determined to eliminate such indirect attacks.^28 Paradoxically, the more assiduously authorities sought to eradicate irony and wit as modes of public criticism, the more firmly entrenched those modes became. Some, like the licenser Sir Roger L’Estrange, argued that forcing heterodox writers to resort to innuendo and witty indirection was actually a good thing. Because they are expressed in a more cautious vein, he argues, modern pamphlets have in fact been rendered less dangerous than controversial works published during the Interregnum. From the standpoint of spreading the gospel of sedition,

the Old Ones have a great Advantage of the New, for being Written in times of Freedom, and Menag’d [sic] by great Masters of the Popular Stile, they speak playner, and stike homer to the Capacity and Humour of the Multitude; whereas they that write in the fear of a Law, are forc’d to cover their Meaning under Ambiguities, and Hints, to the greater Hazzard of the Libeller than of the Publique.^29

For L’Estrange this was a great step forward, but for heterodox writers themselves, the necessity to encode their arguments was a fact to be lamented. Blount mordantly remarks: ‘“Tis a thing of most Dangerous Consequence to Oppose any Doctrine that is publickly receiv’d, how sottish soever it be.” Although Blount had quite cheerfully roasted a glebe-full of sacred cows, beneath his bravado one detects a real fear that “it might fare with me as it did with poor Esop, Who . . . only speaking against Priests of Delphos, cost him his Life.” At one point he recommends the five-year silence of Apollonius. “Words make all men our Enemies, and none but Fools our Friends; therefore, Virsapit, quipauca loquitur. He that makes others afraid of his wit, ought himself to be afraid of their memory; for as much as I have known many men, who (though they could not break a jest) could break a head.”^30 Blount was not alone. As John Toland remarks, “Daily experience sufficiently evinces, that there is no discovering, at least no declaring of TRUTH in most places, but at the hazard of a man’s reputation, imployment, or life.”^31 Toland complains that “Such is the deplorable Condition of our Age, that a Man dares not openly and directly own what he thinks of Divine Matters ... if it but very slightly differs from what is receiv’d by any Party, or that is establish’d by Law; but he is either forc’d to keep perpetual Silence, or to propose his Sentiments to the World by way of Paradox under a borrow’d or fictitious Name.”^32

In response to this state of affairs Toland worked out an elaborate rhetoric of encoding and indirection, subdivided into esoteric and exoteric forms –esoteric writing directed to the initiated, exoteric designed for public consumption. Shaftesbury had predicted that such esotericism would become necessary, pointing out that such strategies of indirection were the natural by products of political repression:

If men are forbid to speak their minds seriously on certain subjects, they will do it ironically. If they are forbid to speak at all upon such subjects, or if they find it really dangerous to do so, they will then redouble their disguise, involve themselves in mysteriousness, and talk so as hardly to be understood, or at least not plainly interpreted by those who are disposed to do them a mischief.^33

Even Warburton, no supporter of Shaftesbury’s defense of ridicule, nonetheless agrees that “a RESTRAINT on free inquiry, will force writers into this vicious manner . . . the only way men have to escape persecution being to cover and intrench themselves in obscurity.”^34

Reviewing this controversy from mid century, Philip Skelton remarks that the deists’ claims of persecution were grossly overstated, as was their defense of disguise, irony, and innuendo. “If you will believe them,” he writes, “they are under a necessity of using stratagem and cunning for these purposes, to prevent the prosecutions to which an opener conduct might expose them in this age of bigotry.” Skelton falls back on a familiar tautology: that deists and freethinkers resorted to rhetorical subterfuge not because they had been forced to do so, but because their arguments would not bear exposure. If they would only argue in an open, decent and manly fashion, Skelton argues, deists and freethinkers would be answered with equivalent civility.^35 Writers like Toland were not convinced. “Nay, I have read of invitations to Heretics, Deists, and Atheists, to speak above ;board; and heard it much lamented, that the books of such were formerly destroy’d, or that they are not suffer’d now to write; because Truth wou’d thereby triumph the more, and these unfortunate men be the more easily reclaim’d.” Now, he argues, “if it be a desirable thing to have the Truth told without disguize, there’s one method to procure such a blessing. Let all men freely speak what they think, without being ever branded or punish’d but for wicked practises, and leaving their speculative opinions to be confuted or approv’d by whoever pleases; then you are sure to hear the whole truth, and till then but very scantily, or obscurely, if at all.”^36 Skelton blithely ignores the force of such arguments: “I can hardly think of a jury capable of frightening these souls of the first magnitude,” he writes, “for not one in ten of them hath been ever prosecuted at law for his book; and such as were, made twice as much by the retail of their counterband wares, as they lost by the prosecution.”^37

Thomas Woolston, of course, was that “one in ten,” first prosecuted for his Moderator Between An Infidel and An Apostate (1725) and then again for Six Discourses of the Miracles of Our Saviour (1727–30). Woolston portrays himself as a writer forced to employ irony and innuendo and he evinces great sympathy for writers like Anthony Collins, whose Discourse on the Grounds and Reasons of the Christian Religion (1724) and Scheme of Literal Prophecy Considered (1726) were currently under attack. “I was afraid the Prosecution of the Moderator, would have deterr’d you from the Press,” Woolston writes of Collins. “Go on then . . . and if you are deny’d the Liberty of the Press, and public Sale of your Books, I hope you’ll for all that, as occasion offers it self, oblige the Learned and Curious with some more of your bright Lucubrations, tho’ you print them, and dispose of them in this clancular and subtil Method.”^38

This “clancular and subtil Method” posed unique problems for those attempting somehow to discourage such works through legal prosecution. For whatever the venue, parliament or King’s Bench, trials for libel increasingly turned on questions of how ironic or indirect argument was to be treated by the court. What had begun with Glanvill and Barrow as an attempt to establish the decorum of wit and ridicule, had become by the early eighteenth century a struggle to define indirect or encoded discourse in such a way that it might be successfully prosecuted. According to A Digest of the Law Concerning Libels, “It seems to be now agreed, that not only Scandal expressed in an open and direct manner, but also such as is expressed in Irony amounts to a Libel.”^39 Another anonymous jurist cites a case under James I, tried in Star Chamber, in which it was established that “ironical Words in Writing, are adjudged libellous; open and sarcastical Reproaches, are allowed, on all Hands to be so. Nothing then remains which may by any Possibility evade the Law, but Writing in Allegory, or . . . Descriptions and Circumlocutions.”^40

The truth of Glanvill’s warning about the irrefutability of jests and loud laughter grew increasingly evident as attorneys for the crown struggled to demonstrate the presence of an actionable irony in the descriptions and circumlocutions of heterodox texts. How was a prosecutor, or a jury for that matter, to determine what was actually meant by particular veiled references in a controversial pamphlet? How were they to determine whether irony was actually present? Whether the works under indictment seemingly attacked the settled principles of Anglican Christianity or British government, prosecutors found themselves uncomfortably circumscribed by the hermeneutic circle. Everyone presumably “knew” what innuendos meant, but how was one to prove that such meanings necessarily inhered in particular utterances, or that they were even intended by the author? In the Sacheverell trial, for example, many of whose arguments turned on such questions of interpretation, Sergeant Parker, one of Sacheverell’s accusers, complained of the difficulty of unraveling indirect rhetoric that everyone understood intuitively, but whose meaning was not otherwise demonstrable.

This is an extraordinary step, that, let a Man cause never so many scandals and reproaches on the government, though in never so public a manner, yet if it be done by way of suggestion and insinuation, and the charges not expressly maintained and avowed, there is no crime in it, nor any high one: That is, in short, sedition and exposing the Government is lawful; only the manner is to be taken Care of. Do not do it directly and avowedly, for that would be dangerous; but do it by suggestions that every body will Understand, and which will have their full Effect, and all’s safe; for those who come to judge you are not to understand you, though every body else does.^41

As we shall see it was precisely the question of the manner of presentation that would prove so damning in the Woolston case.

However tangled such interpretive knots might appear, they were presumably not beyond the ingenuity of the court to untie. Indeed, argues the author of State Law, it is within the power of the court to penetrate those veiled suggestions that “everybody understands” and thus determine the true intention of the author.

From the Reasons of Law, a Libel in Hieroglyphicks, is as much a Libel, and as highly punishable, as an open Invective. If it be really unintelligible to any one, it will pass for Nonsense with every one, and, as such, meet with Impunity; But if there be only a thin Veil, or aukward Disguise thrown over it, thro’ which those who can see and observe may perceive the lurking Satyr within, a Court of Law will examine it narrowly, and judge of it according to the Intention of the Maker, and the Influence it may have upon the injured Party’s Reputation.^42

This version of the court’s prerogative, that it had the power to expose the “lurking Satyr within” esoterically encoded discourse, was by no means adopted unanimously, however. Critics of attempts to prosecute libellous innuendo pointed out that it set a dangerous precedent when officers of the court were allowed to become juridical interpreters of literary texts. Archibald Hutcheson writes that “all the senses clapt upon all heathen authors by their scholiasts, and all the tenets charg’d upon the Inspired Writings by Dutch commentators, were not so wild, absurd, and arbitrary, as what the single force of an innuendo can fix upon any passage, when play’d secundum artem, in the hands of a nice state empirick.”^43 The British Journal argues that any prosecution based upon the interpretation of ironic innuendo poses a greater hazard to British liberty than anything (no matter how offensive) the writer might suggest. “When words used in their true and proper sense, and understood in their literal and natural meaning, import nothing that is criminal, then to strain their genuine signification to make them intend sedition ... is such a stretch of discretionary power, as must subvert all the principles of free government, and overturn every species of liberty.”^44 The problem of determining an author’s meaning was further clouded by the effort to divine his intentions. Theoretically, authorial intention was not relevant to one’s guilt or innocence of the charge of libel. But as State Law makes clear, the court might well seek to demonstrate the “lurking Satyr within” an allegedly libellous text by presuming to elucidate the intentions of its author.^45

III

In a legal climate supercharged with fears of esoteric and hermetic meanings in heterodox texts it was perhaps no accident that Thomas Woolston would be tried for blasphemous libel. Certainly no work of eighteenth century heterodoxy was more custom tailored to test the patience and ingenuity of the court than was Woolston’s Six Discourses of the Miracles of our Saviour (1727–30). At the level of literal exegesis, Woolston argues that “the History of Jesus’s Life, as recorded in the Evangelists, is an emblematic Representation of his spiritual Life in the Soul of Man; and his Miracles are Figures of his mysterious Operations. The four Gospels are in no Part a literal Story, but a System or mystical Philosophy of Theology” (1, p. 65). In practice, however, Woolston’s tracts provide an unrelenting burlesque of the Scriptural account of Jesus’ miracles. His sober protestations notwithstanding, Woolston’s true intentions seemed clear, and such intentions were radical enough to

prove that the literal Story of many of Jesus’s Miracles, as they are recorded in the Evangelists, and commonly believed by Christians, does imply Improbabilities and Incredulities, and the grossest Absurdities, very dishonourable to the Name of Christ; consequently, they, in whole, or in part, were never wrought, but are only related as prophetical and parabolical Narratives of what would be mysteriously and more wonderfully done by him. (1, pp. 19–20)

Woolston’s paradoxical defense of Christ’s Messianic authenticity –by debunking his miracles – struck his critics as completely disingenuous. Indeed, so telling is Woolston’s irony that even a hardened old agnostic like Leslie Stephen dismisses him as a “mere buffoon jingling his cap and bells in a sacred shrine.”^46 Woolston certainly dons an antic disposition. He remarks that gold, frankincense, and myrrh were no proper gifts for either Mary or her child, arguing that if they had brought soap, candles, and sugar instead, the Magi had acted “as wise as well as good Men” (1, p. 56). Such irreverence was bad enough, but worse still was the fact that most of Woolston’s allegorical readings of Scriptural miracles involved ridicule of the church and its hireling clergy. Thus Woolston’s version of Christ’s cleansing of the temple becomes an allegory of the corruptions of the Anglican priesthood. Even the woman with an issue of blood (described by Woolston as a possible nosebleed!) becomes an emblem of the diseases of the church. Worst of all, Christ himself is treated with a witty familiarity that strays well beyond the boundaries of decorum. Woolston’s comparison of Jesus on the Mount of Transfiguration with a theatrical “ Posture Master, ” transforming himself into a “Calf, a Lyon, a Bear, a Ram, a Goat, an Hydra, a Stone, a Tree etc.” (i, p. 42), simply beggared rational refutation.^47

One might multiply instances of Woolston’s wit, but his version of the story of the Gadarene swine will serve by way of example. Woolston raises numerous questions about Jesus’ presumed transference of a legion of devils to a herd of swine, which, according to him, wouldn’t have been in the neighborhood in the first place.

If any Historians but the Evangelists had said so, none would have believed it. The Jews are forbidden to eat Swine’s Flesh; what then should they do with Swine ... who eat neither Pig, Pork, nor Bacon? Some may say that they were kept there for Use of Strangers: but this could not be; because that after Time of Antiochus, who polluted the Temple with the Sacrifice of an Hog, the Jews forbad, under the Pain of an Anathema, the keeping of any Swine in their Country. Perhaps it may be said, that the Gadarens, so call’d from the Place of their Abode, were not Jews, but neighbouring Gentiles, with whom it was lawful to eat, and keep Swine. We will suppose so, tho it is improbable; but then its unlikely (without better Reason than at present we are apprised of) that our Saviour would permit the Devils to enter into a Herd of them to their Destruction. (1, pp. 33–34)

According to the church Jesus’ miracles were all said to be innocent, but where was the goodness of this miracle; what was the use of it? “The Proprietors of the Swine were great Losers and Sufferers; and we don’t read that Jesus made them amends, or that they deserv’d such Usage from him” (1, p. 34). At the very least, Woolston suggests, the Gadarenes might well have sued Christ for damages – and collected.

I know not what our Divines think of this Part of the Story, nor wherefore Jesus escaped so well; but if any Exorcist in this our Age and Nation, had pretended to expel the Devil out of one possess’d, and permitted him to enter into a Flock of Sheep, the People would have said that he had bewitch’d both; and our Laws and Judges too of the last Age, would have made him to swing for it. (1, pp. 34–35)

Whatever its exegetical merits, Woolston’s offhand suggestion – that in the real world Christ would have been hanged for sheepstealing and witchcraft – was guaranteed to offend his readers, and he knew it.

Although Woolston suffered throughout his life from varying degrees of madness, there can be no question that he understood exactly how his works would be received.^48

The reading of this Head will, I doubt not, strike with Horror some of our squeamish Divines, who, notwithstanding they will sacrifice almost any Principles to their Interest, will not bear that our literal evangelical History of such renown’d Miracles should be thus called in Question, and contemptuously spoken of. What does this Author mean, will some say, thus to do Service to Atheism and Infidelity? Away with him! Our Indignation is moved against him! NO Censure and Punishment can be too severe for such Impiety, Profaneness, and Blasphemy, as is aim’d at, and imply’d in this Proposition. (1, p. 20)

Although Woolston was himself an ordained priest of the Church of England, this was hardly the language of one seeking merely to clarify vexed and obscure passages of Scripture. Woolston all but sticks his tongue out at the “little Whisslers in Divinity” (Defence, p. 3), dedicating each of the individual Discourses to one of the bishops who had attacked him: “Use me as roughly in Print as you think fit, I’ll not take it ill. ... I desire nothing more than to be furiously attack’d from the Press, which, if I am not much mistaken, would give me a long’d for Opportunity to expose your Ignorance to more Advantage” (1, pp. 64, 65).

No other heterodox writer went out of his way so to provoke prosecution as did Thomas Woolston. And there is clarity in his purpose, a design to force his critics either to accept his literal argument or to prosecute him on grounds derived largely from an ironic interpretation of his text. Woolston got his wish; he was set upon by such clerics as Edmund Gibson, Bishop of London, who found “the Blasphemous Manner in which [Woolston] has taken the liberty to treat our Saviour’s Miracles and the Author of them” an epitome of all that was most dangerous in heterodox wit. Gibson wishes to make it clear that it is not the substance of Woolston’s argument that offends, however, but the style. “I am far from contending, that the Grounds of the Christian Religion, and the Doctrines of it, may not be discussed at all times, in a calm, decent, and serious way,” Gibson remarks. And he reiterates the common assertion that all Christian practices and beliefs are open to discussion; indeed so powerful and self evident is the case for Christianity that such discussion must necessarily strengthen the orthodox position. Still, he draws the line at ridicule, and “cannot but think it the Duty of the Civil Magistrate at all times, to take care that Religion be not treated either in a ludicrous, or a reproachful manner.”^49

Matthew Tindal responded immediately to the glaring contradictions in Gibson’s argument. Can the Bishop, he asks, “be for punishing a Person, whom he dares not say is in his right Senses, as a Blasphemer, only for the Manner of expressing himself, where the Matter may be lawfully discuss’d?”^50 Tindal points out that were Gibson consistent, he should have thanked Wools ton for providing an occasion for Christianity to triumph yet again over the specious assertions of heterodox wits. And he points out the dubious legality of Gibson’s insistence that Woolston be punished for the style, not the substance of his argument.

Since the Crime of this Clergyman wholly consists, not in discussing the Miracles of our Saviour (for That, ’tis granted, helps to strengthen Christianity,) but in the Manner of doing it; by which he can only have prejudic’d his own Cause, and not That of Christianity; ought not this Writer to have shewn, how That can make the Doing a lawful Thing become not only unlawful, but even blasphemous?^51

Tindal’s argument goes to the heart of the matter. And no one who recommended the prosecution of heterodox wit ever answered his question regarding the miraculous transformation by which the superaddition of a particular rhetorical form could somehow turn an acceptable argument into an actionable offense.

Such subtleties were wasted on Bishop Gibson, who insisted that the civil magistrate prevent all offenses against Christian sensibility, that he effectually “discourage such Books and Writings, as strike equally at the Foundation of all Religion, and of Truth, Virtue, Seriousness, and good Manners; and by consequence, at the Foundation of Civil Society.”^52 One might reasonably question a recommendation that the magistrate punish breaches of “good manners,” yet such was the panic engendered by heterodox wit that otherwise reasonable persons lost all sense of proportion in the face of it. As Tindal points out, Gibson was asking for nothing less than the prosecution of writers for violations of decorum! Anthony Collins, who was equally sensitive to the sweeping implications of this argument, points out the difficulty that must attend any effort to legislate style or manners.

When you draw up your Law, you will find it so very difficult to settle the Point of Decency in Writing, in respect to all the various kinds of Irony and Ridicule, that you will be ready to lay aside your Project; and that you will be no more able to settle that Point of Decency, than you would be to settle by Law, that Cleanliness in Clothes, and that Politeness in Dress, Behaviour, and Conversation, which become Men of Quality and Fortune in the World.

Collins immediately recognizes the ideological agenda at the heart of calls to legislate decorum, suggesting that even if you could determine what constituted a legal standard for good manners, “you will find it very difficult to engage the Lawmakers in your Project. For I am persuaded, that if our Lawmakers were, out of a rational Principle, disposed to give Liberty by Law to a serious Opposition to publickly receiv’d Notions, they would not think it of much Importance to make a Law about a Method of Irony.”^53

But that is precisely what was called for by critics like Richard Smalbroke, Bishop of St. David’s (translated to Lichfield and Coventry in 1731), who sought to “invigorate the Zeal of the Magistrate, in putting the laws in Execution against so flagrant a sort of Profaneness . .. and to convince the World that the Minister of that God, who is so highly Affronted, bears not the Sword in vain.”^54 Here Smalbroke performs the rhetorical hat trick so common to Anglican clerics of the age, simultaneously insisting that ridiculing the church is affronting God directly, that affronting God is endangering the civil polity, and that demanding prosecution is in no wise an infringement of the English liberty from which that polity derived. Of course, no one calling for the suppression ofheterodox texts or the punishment of Woolston ever confessed to a persecutorial motive. Instead, they attempted to redefine irony and ridicule as rhetorical modes fundamentally unlike other forms of argumentation and therefore susceptible to peculiar penalties. Like Gibson, Smalbroke is more than willing to consider the objections against Christianity “when proposed with Decency, or indeed with Indecency in the Present Instance.” But he “cannot be induced to think that there is no real Difference between Arguments and buffoonery, or that licentious Invectives against the Founder of our Religion, and a professed Ridicule of those Miracles that Confirm the Truth of it, are any part of the Liberties of a Christian Nation, or are the only Libels that are not Cognizable by a Christian Magistracy.”^55 So pernicious is ridicule that its very presence signals wicked intentions. To quote Bishop Gibson: “ When you meet with any Book upon the Subject of Religion, that is written in a ludicrous or unserious manner; take it for granted that it proceeds from a deprav’d mind, and is written with an irreligious design.”^56 If another of his gentle critics is to be credited, Woolston’s wit was like the mark of Cain: an invitation to persecution. “If I am grosser in my Expressions, than seems consistent with Christianity, or good Manners,” he argues, “let the Provocation be considered: He can have no Claim to civil Treatment, who runs so foul a Riot on God and Men; and as he has divested himself of all Consideration and Respect of Persons, there can be no Terms too severe for so abominable a Fellow.”^57

There was a specious charm in such arguments that allowed clerics like Gibson and Smalbroke simply to dismiss Woolston’s rights as an Englishman since he had apparently resigned those rights when he chose to be witty. Smalbroke is pleased to explain in detail why punishment for wit ought to be considered fundamentally unlike other forms of prosecution. He argues that Woolston

has, with other Patrons of an Unbounded Liberty, so far abused the true and Legal Notion of Liberty, as to introduce a Licentiousness ... a Liberty to be avowedly Profane and Irreligious, to Deride whatever is Sacred, and blasphemously to Revile the Founder of the Religion which is Professed and Established in these Your Kingdoms: A sort of Liberty, that is so great an Insult on the National Settlement, as to make it evident to all Unprejudiced Persons that Liberty itself ought to have its just Bounds, in order to render it a Blessing to Mankind.^58

Smalbroke argues that since the true ends of government require an established religion, and since established religion becomes thereby part of the constitution, all attempts to bring contempt on that religion promote “the Disturbance of the Peace.”^59 Such is the process, then, by which religious ideology comes to be translated into law; such is the curious chain of argument by which Woolston’s admittedly ludicrous treatment of Scriptural miracles is transformed into a criminal denial of the Act of Settlement.

Of all those clerics who weighed in for the Woolston bout, only Simon Browne was willing to argue that the civil magistrate had no business interfering in cases of religious ridicule. Unlike Shaftesbury, however, Browne makes no case for ridicule as a test of truth. Rather he shrugs it off as an irritating but essentially harmless misuse of rhetoric. He agrees with Gibson and Smalbroke “that there is a. vast difference between . . . ludicrous insult and scurrilous invective, and grave reasonings and manly decent talk.” Yet he is not convinced that laughing at religion does it any “real harm,” or that religion be made “absurd and ridiculous, by senseless cavils, empty jests, and rude invective.”60 Browne is contemptuous of the argument that Woolston’s ridicule of religion somehow threatened the constitution. "‘Magistrates may indeed think their wisdom affronted, and their authority despised, who have thought meet to profess and countenance this religion, if it be reproached; and may resent this, and by prosecutions shew their resentment; but this is really a meer human concern for their own honour, not a Christian concern for the honour of Jesus’s religion.” In fact, Browne argues, magistrates are not directly affronted at all, but only “by implication and innuendo, as far as the reproach of the religion they profess and countenance, involved theirs in it.”^61

Browne was spitting against the wind, for Woolston’s enemies would argue that implication and innuendo were affronts in themselves that could only be controlled with civil prosecution. Upon the publication of Woolston’s Fifth Discourse, Secretary of State Townshend (with the gentle coaxing of Bishop Gibson?) signed a warrant for Woolston’s arrest. And on March 4, 1729 he stood trial at Guildhall on charges of blasphemous libel.^62 Woolston was convicted and sentenced to a year’s imprisonment, with a fine of £ioo (£25 for each of the four Discourses under indictment) and “then to continue in prison for life unless he himself should be bound in a recognizance for £2000, and two others for f iooo each, or four for £500 each, with condition for his good behaviour during life.”^63 Given the nature of the offense, such penalties were stiff indeed. But if they were intended to insure Woolston’s silence – one function of the heavy bond requirements – they failed miserably. While in prison, Woolston produced yet another Discourse and two Defenses of what he had already written.

Woolston was certainly incorrigible, his Discourses undeniably offensive to most sensibilities, but it was necessary to argue that he was dangerous as well. The facts in the case were not in dispute, since Woolston readily admitted to having written the Discourses. And when counsel attempted to move in arrest of judgment in the court of King’s Bench, Chief Justice Raymond answered that the court “would not suffer it to be debated, whether to write against Christianity in general was not an offence punishable in the temporal courts.”^64 Citing the precedent of Rex v. Taylor (1675), Raymond reminded Woolston’s counsel that “Christianity is a parcel of the common law of England . . . now, whatever strikes at the very root of Christianity, tends manifestly to the dissolution of civil government.”^65

As the trial proceeded Attorney General Yorke argued that the Discourses of the Miracles of Our Saviour was “the most Blasphemous Book that ever was Publish’d in any Age whatsoever, in which our Saviour is compared to a Conjurer, Magician and Imposture, and the Holy Ghost, as wrote by the Blessed Evangelists, turn’d into Ridicule and Ludicrous Banter.”^66 The defense responded that the Discourses revealed no such intention. Indeed the outcome of the trial turned on the question of whether or not Woolston had actually intended to ridicule the Gospels. Mr. Birch, Woolston’s counsel, said “He should not dispute that Mr. Woolston did publish this Book, but he could not agree it was done with a Blasphemous Intent, to bring our Religion into Contempt, but to put Our Religion upon a better Footing, and shew, That the Miracles of Our Saviour were to be understood in a Metaphorical Sense, and not as they were Literally Written.” Birch was answered that “If Mr. Woolston’s Intent was to do so, he would not have turn’d the Miracles of Our Saviour into Ridicule, and Proceeded in so Ludicrous a Manner, as he has done, but to have endeavour’d to prove, They were not to be taken as they are Litterally Wrote, by a Serious Discourse and Sound Argument.”^67 The Attorney General’s argument seems to echo the sentiments of Bishop Gibson, that heterodox writing was acceptable only if pursued in a sober and genteel fashion. The court having accepted the argument that ridicule was itself proof of depraved intent, Woolston’s conviction rested largely on the construction of his irony, and innuendo. Had it been concluded that he was indeed serious about his attempts to put religion on a better footing, Woolston would have been vindicated. But as the prosecution argued, the mere fact of their being witty was prima facie evidence of the libellous intent of Woolston’s Discourses. This is certainly the construction that Woolston himself placed upon his conviction. As Henry Stebbing, one of Woolston’s critics, recounts the trial, Woolston was “prosecuted, he tells us, for the Style and Strain of his Writings, that is, I suppose, for burlesquing and ridiculing the Miracles of our Blessed Saviour.”^68

Woolston was absolutely right; the court had responded to calls for a peculiar vengeance like those issued by Bishop Smalbroke, who argued that such is the threat posed by ironic discourse, that it ought to be answered with the most draconian penalties. “And tho’ all such Attempts, whether Serious or ludicrous, are punishable by Common–Law,” argues Smalbroke, “yet they are not, as is pretended by Mr. W. all equally punishable; since Ludicrous Attempts of that kind, and especially as attended with those that are Serious, which explain the Design of the Ridicule, carry with them a greater Contempt of the Authority of the Constitution, and therefore a fortiori Demand a proportionable Punishment.”^69 In other words, because they pose a more serious threat to the constitution, witty libels deserve more severe punishment than do libels presented in a more sober fashion.

If nothing else, Woolston’s conviction offered a clear warning to other heterodox writers that ridicule and burlesque would not be tolerated.^70 Although prosecutions for blasphemous libel were infrequent for the rest of the eighteenth century, they tended to follow the precedents laid down with the Woolston case. Indeed by the first decade of the nineteenth century it had become a settled conclusion that “blasphemy against the Deity in general, or attack upon the Christian religion individually, for the purpose of exposing its doctrines to contempt and ridicule, is indictable.”^71 In 1841 a Royal Commission claimed that “all the recorded instances of prosecution for blasphemy, subsequent to Woolston’s case, have been publications of indecent and opprobrious language.” As a result all sentences were based “entirely upon the offensive manner of writing.”^72 We begin in the seventeenth century with the argument that jests and loud laughter are not to be confuted and conclude with a legal consensus that religious ridicule is a fit object for civil prosecution. So threatening was wit that the preservation of orthodoxy required not only the control of heterodox ideas but the proscription of the rhetorical modes in which those ideas were embodied. While the Augustans may have released the genie of wit, they found it more difficult to restrain him when he proved unruly or even dangerous. But, the argument went, if you couldn’t coax the genie back in the lamp, at least you could try to put him in jail, which is where, in 1733, Thomas Woolston died.^73

NOTES

The phrase is that of John Dowel, The Leviathan Heretical (1683), but of the contemporary attacks on Leviathan listed in the bibliography to S. I. Mintz’s The Hunting of Leviathan (Cambridge, 1962), some two dozen pamphlets complain of Hobbes’s wit, ambiguity, trickery, and entrapment.
See Mary Astell, Bartlemy Fair; Or, An Enquiry After Wil (1709). Richard Blackmore, A Satyr Against Wit (1700). Edward Hyde, Earl of Clarendon, A Brief View and Survey of the Dangerous and Pernicious Errors to the Church and State in Mr. Hobbes’s Book Entitled Leviathan (1676).
Isaac Barrow, “Against Foolish Talking and Jesting,” (1678) in The Theological Works of Isaac Barrow, D. D., ed. Alexander Napier, 9 vols. (Cambridge, 1859), n, p. 3.
Joseph Glanvill, A Blow at Modern Sadducism in Some Philosophical Considerations About Witchcraft (London, 1668), p. 152.
William Warburton, “To the Free Thinkers,” The Divine Legation of Moses, rptd. In The Works of the Right Reverend William Warburton, 7 vols. (London, 1788), 1, pp. x–xi.
Jeremy Collier, Miscellanies Upon Moral Subjects, The Second Part (London, 1695), epistle dedicatory.
Representation of the Present State of Religion with Regard to the Late Excessive Growth of Injidelity, Heresy, and Profaneness (London, 1711), p. 4.
On Shaftesbury’s defense of wit, see A. O. Aldridge, “Shaftesbury and the Test of Truth,” PMLA, 60 (1945), 129–56. Charles Blount had preceded Shaftesbury in his insistence that wit and ridicule ought not to be censored. Blount argues, for example, that he cannot find any censorship among the ancients. “Neither do we read of any Decree against the Satyrical sharpness <:>[Lucilius, Catullus, or Flaccus.” Indeed as if meeting the enemy on his own terms, Blount denies the common argument that the sentence of death against Socrates was facilitated because Aristophanes had first made him ridiculous. “We do not find amongst the Greeks, that their Vetus Comedia (which was so much censured for Libelling and Traducing Men by Name as to be prohibited Acting on the Stage) was ever supprest from being read, but rather the contrary; for that Plato himself recommended the Reading of Aristophanes (the loosest of all those old Comedians) to his Royal Scholar Dionysus.” (Charles Blount, A Just Vindication of Learning and the Liberty of the Press (1695), rptd. in Miscellaneous Works [London, 1695], pp. 5–6).
Daniel Defoe, An Essay on the Regulation of the Press (1704), ed. John Robert Moore (Oxford, 1948), pp. 3–4.
Indeed as Charles Blount would remark, any return to a system of licensing would almost certainly strike hardest at the wits of the age. “Heaven grant,” Blount writes, “that in time, there be not the same Restraint and Monopoly over Witty Discourse, as there is now over Ingenious Writing.” Vindication, pp. 15–16.
Charles Leslie, A Supplement Upon Occasion of A History of Religion (1694), rptd. in The Theological Works of the Rev. Charles Leslie, 7 vols. (Oxford, 1832), n, p. 661. A few, like the author of the Memoirs of the Life and Writings of Matthew Tindall, LL.D. (1723), saw both the savagery and silliness of demands for civil prosecution. For “whenever Church Power, or the Church Interest, is attacked, all Ecclesiastics in the Universe are in a high Delirium, and Inquisitions and Bulls, in Romish Countries; the Power of the Kirk, in Scotland, and Crown Informations in England, are the constant Caustics which are applied to the poor Laity. While the Priesthood aloud continually do cry, the Secular Arm! the Secular Arm! in that alone, is our Refuge” (p. 12). >Indeed as Charles Blount would remark, any return to a system of licensing would almost certainly strike hardest at the wits of the age. “Heaven grant,” Blount writes, “that in time, there be not the same Restraint and Monopoly over Witty Discourse, as there is now over Ingenious Writing.” Vindication, pp. 15–16.
Leonard Levy, Treason Against God: A History of the Offense of Blasphemy 12 (New York, 1981), pp. 314–16.
Laurence Hanson, Government and the Press 1695–1763 (Oxford, 1936), p. 17. 13
Daniel Defoe, The Review, 1: (August 12, 1704). 14
A Complete Collection of State Trials, ed. T. B. Howell, 33 vols. (London, 15 1812), xiv, p. 1127.
Barrow, “Of Foolish Talking and Jesting,” 11, p. 3. 16
A Digest of the Law Concerning Libels (London, 1765), p. 57. 17
G. D. Nokes, A History of the Crime of Blasphemy (London, 1928), p. 49. 18
Warburton, “To the Free Thinkers,” 1, p. xxiii. 19
Levy, Treason Against God, p. 327. For the most complete account of the 20 Aikenhead trial see Michael Hunter, ‘“Aikenhead the Atheist’: The Context and Consequences of Articulate Irreligion in the Late Seventeenth Century,” in Atheism from the Reformation to the Enlightenment (Oxford, 1992), PP– 221–54. ...
The line between outright blasphemy and seditious libel was blurry at 21 best. For a history of the prosecution of blasphemous libels, see Levy, Treason Against God, pp. 297–330, and Donald Thomas, A Long Time Burning: The History of Literary Censorship in England (London, 1969), pp. 63–73. See, also, Nokes, Crime of Blasphemy, William Holdsworth, A History of the English Law (London, 1938), vm, pp. 333–78; James Fitzjames Stephen, A History of the Criminal Law in England (London, 1883), 11, pp. 397–497.
Holdsworth, English Law, vm, p. 407. 22
John Turner, A Vindication of the Rights and Privileges of the Christian Church 23 (London, 1707), preface, pp. xxii, v.
On the rather slipshod procedure by which works were singled out for 24 prosecution, see Samuel Hilliard, A Narrative of the Prosecution of Mr. Sare and His Servant, for Selling the Rights of the Christian Church (London, 1709).
Thomas Lathbury, History of the Convocation (London, 1853), pp. 348–51. 25
For a full inventory of all those works burned, see Charles Ripley Gillett, 26 Burned Books: Neglected Chapters in British History and Literature, 2 vols. (New York, 1932), 11, pp. 667–702.
Ibid., 11, p. 590. 27
For a record of prosecutions of blasphemy at common law, see Nokes, 28 Crime of Blasphemy, pp. 147–67.
Roger L’Estrange, Considerations and Proposals in Order to the Regulation of the 29 Press (London, 1663), pp. 9–10.
Charles Blount, Two First Books of Philostratus Concerning the Life of 30 Apollonius Tyaneus (London, 1680), p. 55, preface.
John Toland, “Clidophorus,” Tetradymus (London, 1720), p. 67. 31
John Toland, Christianity Not Mysterious (London, 1696), preface, pp. 4–5. 32
Shaftesbury, Characteristics of Men, Manners, Opinions, Times (1711), ed. 33 John M. Robertson 2 vols. (1900; rptd. Indianapolis, 1964), 1, p. 50. For a fuller analysis of the mechanics of indirection in heterodox texts, see David Berman, “Deism, Immortality, and the Art of Theological Lying,” in J. A. Leo Lemay (ed.), Deism, Masonry, and the Enlightenment, (Newark, DE, 1987), pp. 61–78; and “Disclaimers as Offense Mechanisms in Charles Blount and John Toland,” in Michael Hunter and David Wootton (eds.), Atheism from the Reformation to the Enlightenment (Oxford, ’992), PP– 255–72.
Warburton, “To the Free–Thinkers,” 1, pp. xxvi–xxvii. 34
Philip Skelton, Ophiomach.es: Or, Deism Revealed ed. David Berman 2 vols. 35 (’749; rptd– Bristol, 1990), n, p. 373.
Toland, “Clidophorus,” pp. 95–96. 36
Skelton, Ophiomaches, n, pp. 373–74. 37
Thomas Woolston, Six Discourses of the Miracles of Our Saviour, and Defences 38 of His Discourses (1727–30; rptd. New York and London, 1979), first discourse, p. 68. All quotations from Woolston are taken from this edition and are quoted in the text by discourse and page number.
A Digest of the Law Concerning Libels, p. 6. 39
State Law, or the Doctrine of Libels Discussed and Examined (London, 1729), p. 58. 40
State Trials, xv, pp. 183–84. In Vindicius Liberius (1702) Toland lays out 41 his own strategy for interpreting ambiguous but potentially heterodox texts: “We are ... oblig’d to make the most candid Construction of their Designs, and if their words admit of a double sense, (which is hard to be always avoided in any Language) we ought to allow the fairest interpretation of their Meaning” (p. 6); quoted in Berman, “The Art of Theological Lying,” p. 64.
42 State Law, p. 74. This pamphleteer further argues that “Courts ofjustice may be directed by the received Opinion, by the Sense of the World, and not stick to the literal Sense of Words,” since “Words have been adjudged scandalous, which, from the bare Meaning, no Scholar could find any harm in” (p. 59).
The Freeholder’s Journal, 36 (September 1722). 43
British Journal, 6 (October 27, 1722). For Defoe as well the importance of 44 innuendo as a determinant in libel verdicts was worrisome, particularly when there was no case law outlining exactly what constituted libel in the first place. “The crime of an Author is not known; and I think verily no Book can be wrote so warily, but that if the Author be brought on his Tryal, it shall be easy for a cunning lawyer, ay for a Lawyer of not great Cunning, to put an innuendo upon his meaning, and make some Part of it Criminal” (Defoe, Essay, p. 20).
Nokes, Crime of Blasphemy, pp. 67–69. 45
Leslie Stephen, History of English Thought in the Eighteenth Century, 2 vols. (1876; rptd. New York, 1949), 1, p. 232.
For a survey of the arguments in the Discourses, see William H. Trapnell, “What Thomas Woolston Wrote,” British Journal for Eighteenth Century Studies, 14 (Spring 1991), 13–30.
William Trapnell, “Who Thomas Woolston Was,” British Journal for Eighteenth Century Studies, 11 (1988), 143–58.
Edmund Gibson, The Bishop of London’s Pastoral Letter to the People of his Diocese (London, 1728), p. 35.
Matthew Tindal, An Address to the Inhabitants of the Two Great Cities of 5° London and Westminster in Relation to a Pastoral Letter Said to be Written by the Bishop of London (London, 1729), p. 25.
Ibid., p. 20. 51
Gibson, Pastoral Letter, p. 35. 52
Anthony Collins, A Discourse Concerning Ridicule and Irony in Writing (London, 1729), p. 26.
Richard Smalbroke, A Vindication of the Miracles of Our Blessed Saviour, vol. 1 (London, 1729), dedication to the Queen Regent.
Richard Smalbroke, A Vindication of the Miracles of Our Blessed Saviour, vol. 11 (London, 1731), dedication, A4.
Gibson, Pastoral Letter, p. 8.
For God Or the Devil, Or, Just Chastisement No Persecution (London, 1729), p. 17. The claim that Woolston had run “riot” was one which came easily to those involved in suppressing nonconformity of various kinds. In 1673, leaders of a Jewish synagogue in London were indicted for a “riot” that had consisted of praying in their synagogue (Levy, Treason Against God, p. 319). For other attacks on Woolston’s style, see Nathaniel Lardner, A Vindication of Three of Our Blessed Saviour’s Miracles (London, 1729); An Expostulary Letter to Mr. Woolston, on Account of His Late Writings, By a Clergyman in the Country (London, 1730); Thomas Ray, A Vindication of Our Saviour’s Miracles, in Answer to Mr. Woolston’s Five Last Discourses (London, 1730).
Smalbroke, Vindication, 11, dedication.
This was an expansive but thoroughly dubious legal claim. Writing long after the issue had ceased to inspire such fierce passions, a jurist reminds his readers of Coke’s early argument that “slanderous words are not a breach of behaviour, for tho’ such words are motives and mediate provocations for breach of the peace, yet tend they not immediately to a breach of the peace like a challenge.” (A Letter Concerning Libels, Warrants, the Seizing of Papers and Sureties of Behaviour, 3rd edn [1765], p. 40).
Simon Browne, A Fit Rebuke to a Ludicrous Infidel: In some Remarks on Mr. Woolston’s Fifth Discourse on the Miracles of Our Saviour, (London, 1732), p. iii.
Ibid., p. v.
On the conduct of Woolston’s trial, see Trapnell, “Who Woolston Was,” I49–51.
Hypatia Bonner, Penalties Upon Opinion (London, 1943), p. 35.
Nokes, Crime of Blasphemy, p. 63.
Holdsworth, English Law, vm, p. 408.
An Account of the Trial of Thomas Woolston, B.D. (London, 1729), p. 1.
Ibid., p. 1.
Henry Stebbing, A Defence of the Scripture History (London, 1730), p. v.
Smalbroke, Vindication, pp. x–xi.
Certainly the prosecutor’s summary of the case leads toward the conclusion that because they undermine the Civil Constitution, innuendos against God deserve peculiar punishments. “The Laws of God, as was observ’d by the Council, are a Part, and the Chief Part of the Laws of this Kingdom; and if a Man, who should write against our stated Laws, or but to turn them into Burlesque and Ridicule, cannot escape with Impunity, what can he expect, who shall strike at the Root of Christianity, and bring into Contempt the Author and Finisher of our Faith.” Account, p. 6.
Charles Bradlaugh, The Laws Relating to Blasphemy and Heresy: An Address to Freethinkers (London, 1878), p. 19.
Levy, Treason Against God, p. 335.
Incarcerated “within the rules” of King’s Bench prison, Woolston actually had considerable freedom of movement, and did not die in close confinement. On the conditions of Woolston’s imprisonment, see Trapnell, “Who Thomas Woolston Was,” 151–52.